Guide to the Samuel Bowles Papers
Yale University Library
- Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts
  - Bowles discusses in this unascribed letter the position of the Phelps suit against the Republican [copy], 1856
    - Barton S. Jones, a correspondent of the Indianapolis Journal, encloses an accompanying article on Senator Mortin, which he could not have published at his home., 1877 May 23
    - G. I. Jones, publisher, writes Bowles a letter of agreement with the choice of Charles Francis Adams for president in 1876., 1875 Dec 13
    - C. P. Kimball discusses with Bowles an orator at Cincinnati. Bowles and Kimball want Charles Francis Adams., 1875 Nov 23
    - Rose G. Kingsley hopes Bowles will be kindly disposed toward her cousin, W. Leighton Hope-Edwards, who will visit the states., 1874 Nov 1
    - L. Q. C. Lamar sends Bowles a telegram saying that Blaine had approved and advises a mission of Lamar's. He tells Bowles to modify his criticism so that the people can hear., 1875
    - Perry Arthur Latham discusses with Bowles the prominence given to Walker's speech at Amherst. Latham thinks that Walker deserves praise, but he also says that some of the ideas were original in a book of his., 1874 Aug 1
    - Richard Lathus sends a thank you for a letter. He says to Bowles that liberal-minded men scarcely change politics or religion., 1876 Sep 20
    - Richard Lathus found favor from Bowles at the Manhattan Club. He discusses the hospitality between South Carolina and Massachusetts on a social occasion. He feels a decadence in political moral convictions., 1876 Dec 18
    - Lodge gives a report on the activities of the Republican Party at this time with a discussion of the National Convention., 1875 Dec 18
    - Henry Cabot Lodge was assistant editor of the North American Review when this letter was written. He states that they are trying to do work in the Republican Party as Bowles had. He does not want the party to have to go back to the Independent Movement., 1875 Dec 23
    - Lodge is issuing invitations to an undesignated event., 1876 May 4
    - Henry Cabot Lodge thanks Bowles for his foresight in the Senate paralysis. He asks for help from Bowles on the subject of taxation., 1877 Sep 17
    - S. Maltby acknowledges a letter from Bowles; he says that Spaulding would be good but he cannot afford a campaign., 1872 May 24
    - R. H. Mathus thanks Bowles for writing an admirable article on the president of Amherst., 1876 Jun 9
    - William Gordon McCabe calls to Bowles' mind a pleasant voyage across the Atlantic, which they shared. He suggests an exchange between the Index of Petersburg, Virginia, and the Republican., 1872 May 15
    - George S. Merriam sends Bowles a copy of his book,., 1877 Apr 11
    - Merriam acknowledges a letter from Bowles. He indicates knowledge of a Bowles trip to Kentucky and Colorado., 1877 Jun 11
    - Merriam tells Bowles that one must go abroad to know what a good paper the Republican was., 1877 Aug 20
    - George S. Merriam first writes an apology for having taken so much of Bowles' time on the twenty-fifth. Merriam says that his family has been hurt by the Republican attitude towards Beecher., n.y. Nov 26
    - Donald Grant Mitchell (Ik Marvel) wants a copy of the semi-weekly Republican., no date
    - John B. Morgan in Paris apologizes to Bowles for not having been able to see his brother before he lost., 1876 Jun 17
    - John Lothrop Motley apologizes to Bowles for being late in the receipt of the copy of Across the Continent., 1866 Jul 30
    - Musgrave writes Bowles that he had gone to Gov. Morgan's reception for Halstead of Cincinnati. He says that he found it cold and formal., 1876 Oct 29
    - Thomas Nast had looked for Bowles' name announcing his arrival in Washington but could not find it. He apologizes for not having gone on a proposed excursion, but his work kept him., 1877 Jun 7
    - Nordhoff tells Bowles that he too believes in Hayes., 1876 Oct 15
    - Nordhoff has just returned from Washington, as he writes this letter to Bowles. He discusses the fact that Springfield does not have a standard line to New York., 1877 Feb 21
    - Nordhoff speaks to Bowles of his children. He states that the Republican has been good to them., 1877 Feb 21
    - Nordhoff speaks in pity to Bowles, since Blaine has made such a hit with the country., 1877 Jun 16
    - Nordhoff tells Bowles that he forgot to mail him a book on the George T. Davis obituary., 1877 Jun 27
    - The grain war has just finished, and Nordhoff asks Bowles if he has ever swung the deceitful scythe., 1877 Jul 30
    - Nordhoff points out the slowness of Hayes to Bowles. He says that Hayes always thinks that tomorrow is another day. He fears that the country is going to pieces., 1877 Aug 16
    - Nordhoff relates that Bartlett gave him an account of Bowles, and that he is worried about him., 1877 Oct 16
    - Charles Eliot Norton writes Bowles that he has a sermon which was delivered in the first parish of Springfield, Oct 16, 1775. He says that it contains historical narrative on early Springfield and wants to know if Bowles cares to reprint it., 1875 Nov 12
    - Francis W. Palfrey talks of a fund for Bartlett's family. He thinks that the fund should not be made public., 1876 Dec 16
    - Elizabeth L. Parker thanks Bowles for being kind during her mother's death., 1865 Jun 5
    - John Pierce thanks Bowles for a kind remembrance., 1874 Jan 6
    - Robert Pomeroy thanks Bowles for a tribute to Seth Pomeroy., 1875 Nov 10
    - W. M. Pomeroy has discussed with Bowles a possible candidate for Congress and is thus far disappointed., 1874 Oct 17
    - A. K. Potter discusses a news article with Bowles, containing a personal reference to the Phelps affair., no date
    - Thomas R. Potter acknowledges a letter from Bowles. He had not had a reply of the U.S. on certain unmentioned questions, but he felt safe due to the good will of Americans., 1872 May 1
    - N. Price tells Bowles that he is too good and mean to spoil him. He speaks of an interview at the N.Y. Tribune which was Halstead's doing., 1874 Oct 1
    - N. A. Priest writes Bowles of a Miss Stebbins who has not had experience teaching., 1860 Apr 24
    - E. Armstrong Reed returns a letter sent to her by Griffin or Bowles. She says that the letter is kind in its expressions against her and says the false impression of Mr. Bowles to personal friends shall be removed., 1877 May 2
    - Alexander Hamilton Rice tells Bowles that he has read the Republican and that Bowles has a progressive view of the state. He congratulates him on being discriminating and candid., 1875 Aug 16
    - B. Rice tells Bowles that a spiel on clerical education was not kindly received., 1874 Nov 2
    - Lizzie D. Rice writes Bowles that she did not look for unexpected congratulations on correspondent work. She discussed Branciard, whom she is going to marry., 1874 Mar 28
    - Abby Faye Richardson thanks Bowles for his friendship to her and her husband., 1870 Jun 11
    - Runkle jokingly discusses some domestic problems with Bowles., 1870 Nov 15
    - Runkle discusses women's suffrage with Bowles and speaks briefly of the Grant administration., 1872 Sep 11
    - Runkle speaks of the Republican to Bowles and a certain Mr. Colfax., 1872 Dec 18
    - This Runkle letter is incomplete., 1872 Dec 22
    - Runkle sends a check for a new issue of the Republican and gives much praise for the worthiness of the paper., 1873 Mar 2
    - Runkle merely discusses a private visit with Bowles., 1874 Jan 12
    - L. G. Runkle first discusses an article with Bowles on the Smith sisters who do not pay their taxes to protest that women cannot vote. He declaims the writers of this article as unfeeling to the cause of the Smith sisters., 1874 Jan 19
    - Runkle discussed the question of faith with Bowles., 1874 Feb 12
    - Runkle suggests that Bowles is a little unjust to Beecher., 1875 Feb 12
    - Runkle talks to Bowles of a mutual friend who is now married., 1875 Jun 10
    - Runkle speaks to Bowles of an Edith Lee who is now on the stage., 1876 Apr 4
    - L. G. Runkle jokingly writes Bowles that he should come and give him a lesson on morals on his return., 1876 Apr 19
    - Runkle writes Bowles that he believes the Republican has convicted Beecher before the trial is over., n.y. Apr 5
    - Russell wants to know if he must always lecture Bowles on legislation. He has noticed that Bowles speaks well of Heister Clymer of Pennsylvania., 1874 Feb 5
    - Russell cannot understand why Bowles was angry over the Ward matter when he had already made up his mind to do what he could., 1874 Mar 12
    - Russell had received an Ian Ialfred Townsend letter from Bowles' office and could not understand why he received it., 1875 Aug 29
    - Russell apologizes for not having written Bowles in so long. He suggests a meeting between Bowles and Billy Collins. He says he is going to work on his book Spanish Conquest of Central America., 1875 Nov 19
    - Russell discusses the pecuniary end of writing for the Republican with Bowles., 1875 Dec 25
    - Russell writes Bowles that by having to keep company with a Dutch professor he must be having to expiate for some crime. Additionally, he thinks that Blaine has at last ruined himself politically., 1876 Jan 16
    - Russell tells Bowles that the Republican supported C. E. Billings for U.S. District Judge in LA, as the Republican supported all sorts of scalawags., 1876 Jan 22
    - Russell writes Bowles a letter telling him what he is doing, such as an accident in which he fell down the back steps., 1876 Feb 7
    - Russell talks to Bowles of the death of a mutual friend, Denison., 1876 Feb 21
    - Russell briefly speaks to Bowles of Washburn, Blaine, and Tilden., 1876 Mar 27
    - Russell thinks that Bowles' reply to him on the Indian legislation was especially unkind., 1876 Jun 1
    - Russell tells Bowles that Grant's orders contain wise words coupled with indiscreet action, as the appointment of Sheridan of Louisiana. He also says he dislikes Hayes., 1876 Nov 14
    - Russell tells Bowles that literary men in politics become very poor. He gives Bret Hart as an example., 1877 Jun 18
    - Russell writes Bowles that the Radicals are trying to rehabilitate Chamberlain of South Carolina., 1877 Sep 24
    - Franklin B. Sanborn writes a poem to Samuel Bowles on his birthday - "With a Handful of Flowers.", 1869 Feb 9
    - Schurz apologizes for not having answered Bowles' last letter and for not stopping in Springfield on a recent trip., 1871 Jul 4
    - Schurz thanks Bowles for some kind remarks in his column. Schurz discusses the outcome of the Cincinnati Convention for Republicans., 1872 May 11
    - Schurz tells Bowles that he may not be able to call on him at a prescribed time. He confides in Bowles that he intends to devote himself to literary pursuits at the close of his senatorial career. He has thought of doing a political history of the United States and would like advice from Bowles as to the publisher., 1874 Nov 27
    - Schurz discusses a Mr. Allen who might run as the "candidate for both parties.", 1875 Nov 23
    - Schurz tells Bowles that he does not consider it wise to be a demonstrator for Charles Francis Adams at this time., 1876 Jan 4
    - Schurz agrees with Bowles that Blaine has killed himself as a candidate., 1876 Jan 16
    - Schurz discusses the Belknap case that has changed the whole picture. He thinks Charles Francis Adams will come into the picture again but discusses a possible second choice., 1876 Mar 7
    - Schurz discusses the intention to hold a conference at Cincinnati on Apr 27 and has among the invitations: William Cullen Bryant, President Woolsey, Governor Bullock. He wants Bowles to get Newton Booth's signature., 1876 Mar 27
    - Schurz says that Gov. Bullock is unwilling to attend the convention, since he feels that no sufficient number of respectable Massachusetts men would attend the conference. He asks Bowles to use his influence to get him to sign., 1876 Mar 29
    - Schurz relates to Bowles that Charles Francis Adams, Jr. has stopped by and advised Schurz not to invite Seelye to the Cincinnati movement. Schurz wants Bowles to ask him personally., 1876 Apr 2
    - Schurz writes Bowles that he had received Bullock's signature. He acknowledges that he had received Booth's declination., 1876 Apr 3
    - Schurz tells Bowles of the acceptance of an invitation to a certain event., 1876 Apr 6
    - Schurz merely acknowledges a letter., 1877 Aug 22
    - Schurz mentions that there are rumblings about himself as Secretary of the Interior., 1877 Aug 29
    - Schurz states that the air is somewhat clearer in the Department of the Interior. He congratulates Bowles on his work in Massachusetts., 1877 Sep 30
    - L. L. Schuyler writes Bowles that he should take a vacation for his health as she is doing for hers. She discusses the possibility of men and women working together., 1873 Aug 8
    - Louisa Lee Schuyler sends Bowles a note including a publication issued by the State Charities Aid Association. She hopes Bowles will review the publication in the Republican., 1877 Apr 30
    - Robert Schweichel thanks Bowles for theprivilegeof seeing his letters and of translating them into his native tongue. He tells Bowles that many German newspapers have published voluminous extracts of the letters. He hopesfor the election of Grant and Colfax as a symbol of freedom., 1869 Feb 28
    - Harvey Whitefield Scott is impressed with Bowles' insistence on the moral side of the Bowles-Field correspondence., 1871 Feb 23
    - Seelye tells Bowles that he is sorry to turn down an invitation. He says that he will have no part in Congressional contests. He believes politics are very corrupt at this time., 1874 Oct 10
    - Seelye would not allow his name to be signed to the paper for a New York political meeting organized by Schurz and Bowles, since he would not be attending., 1875 Apr 10
    - Seelye speaks to Bowles of the Speakership Contest; yet he plans to stay out of the Democratic caucus., 1875 Dec 2
    - Seelye says that McKerr has been nominated from the caucus which was controlled by Tammany., 1875 Dec 4
    - Seelye tells Bowles that a brother from Easthampton in Congress might stop the "Butlerizing" campaign., 1876 Sep 16
    - Mary E. Short thanks Bowles for a notice of Mrs. Short's address., 1866 Jul 28
    - Lynlph Slanley thanks Bowles for a copy of his book Across the Continent., 1866 Jan 10
    - Smalley writes Bowles about various newspapers and his admiration for Whitelaw Reid as a journalist., 1874 Feb 17
    - Smalley writes Bowles as to what to do with a Senate filled with political accomplices of Butler., 1876 Apr 15
    - Smalley writes Bowles a friendly note, telling him about his plans as a correspondent., 1876 Aug 5
    - Smalley discusses the professional plans of Waite and Schurz with Bowles., 1877 Apr 9
    - George Washburn Smalley asks for a subscription to the Republican., n.y. Jun 27
    - Phoebe Garnaut Smalley, wife of George W. Smalley, sends a note of thanks to Bowles for a picture sent to her., 1876 Dec 24
    - G. T. Spaulding writes Bowles that he has been shown a letter in which Bowles has suggested him as a candidate for Congress. Spaulding does not want his name suggested., 1872 May 27
    - A letter from James R. Spaulding expresses admiration for an article on a Henry J. Raymond. He thinks his part has been misjudged., 1869 Jun 21
    - Spaulding asks Bowles why Maltby cannot be brought forward as a reform candidate for Congress., 1876 Aug 22
    - George W. Stearns discusses disbelief in a libel suit against Bowles., 1873 Dec 6
    - Stebbins talks of a trip along the west side of a California valley, which Bowles took. He wants to build a farm where the San Joaquin River connects the valley and lease areas to tenants. He hopes Bowles will make this known in the East., 1873 Jun 21
    - Horatio Stebbins hopes Bowles' good feelings did not make him speak too kindly of Stebbins. He tells Bowles that California politics are terrible, especially the vulgarity of the press. Stebbins says that Newton Booth has been damaged due to an open tirade against Gorham. He fears that too much political blame has been put on William Chapman Ralston. He feels that in the bank situation in California an attempt has been made to cover personal responsibility by putting full blame on Ralston., 1875 Sep 9
    - Stebbins tells Bowles that it is impossible for him to go to Amherst on a suggested trip., 1876 Jun 29
    - Alexander Turney Steward acknowledges the pleasure of having Bowles over to dinner., no date
    - Charles Sumner acknowledges a note from Bowles., 1872 Mar 14
    - Charles Sumner discusses an affair in the Senate, 1874., 1874 Mar 3
    - Charles Sumner writes Bowles that Mr. Waite of Ohio has been nominated for Chief Justice and Bowles has denounced Sumner in a speech., no date
    - Allen Thayer writes Bowles that he thinks the attack of George Hoar in the Republican will work great injury to them. He says that Hoar is sensitive and fully believes that the Republican is out to break him. He says that Hoar is an honest man and asks Bowles to quit his chastisement of him., 1875 Mar 6
    - Allen Thayer asks Bowles if it is quite the sense of justice to associate his name with thosewhomhe has opposed for many years. He points out that he has taken no active interest in politics, only in the practice of his profession., 1875 Mar 23
    - Allen Thayer wishes to discuss an up-and-coming campaign with Bowles. He wants to see the effect the Mississippi campaign could have on the presidential election., 1875 Oct 4
    - Allen Thayer talks of the contemptuous loss of trust by Bowles in him. Thayer says that he has aided in the campaign to defeat the Rice opponent before Adams' name was mentioned., 1876 Mar 29
    - Allen Thayer tells Bowles that he will not ask anybody to vote for Rice at the convention, though he sees no objection to his candidacy except that he was not strong in country towns. He says he feels that Bowles has never understood that exact position., 1876 Apr 3
    - Francis Tiffany thanks Bowles for a pamphlet containing the Field controversy letters., 1871 Mar 29
    - Francis Tiffany writes that he is sorry about the death of Bowles' brother., 1876 May 16
    - Osmond Tiffany writes Bowles a letter of introduction for Joseph Henry Rieman who wants to ask Bowles if Rev. Mr. Reed will be a good pastor., 1876 Mar 25
    - Anna M. Tilcomb talks of the fine beginning of the Hayes administration. She briefly speaks of the Negro question and gives an intimation on women's suffrage., 1866 Mar
    - Francis Amasa Walker congratulates Bowles on the result of his trial and adds a brief discussion of national politics., 1875 May 6
    - Walker (George) writes Bowles that he has told Dawes that the anti-Butler campaign was enough to elect him., 1874 Mar 12
    - Samuel Ward thanks Bowles for an expression of regret to him. Ward lists a number of bad names he has been called: pervasive, card shard, billiard expert, disreputable., 1874 Mar 6
    - Ward apologizes for not having been aware of Bowles' illness. He discusses the fact that a lot of humbugs are in the lobby., 1874 Mar 30
    - Annie D. Ware wants Bowles to use his influence to get her on the stage., 1877 May 21
    - George C. Warr, the secretary of the Cabden Club, writes Bowles that the club is about to republish an edition on State of Land Tenure, 1870-1871. He tells Bowles that he may have a new copy., 1876 Mar 9
    - William Washburn dislikes Bowles' paper suggesting that he would like to return to Washington., 1876 Aug 25
    - Henry Watterson says that he and Gov. Hangen conducted an inquest on Bowles' life and character., 1873 Feb 21
    - Henry Watterson tells Bowles that he is to orate in Indiana., 1873 Mar 18
    - Henry Watterson compliments Bowles' integrity, calling him "dear old humbug and wretched old Yankee.", 1873 Nov 29
    - Henry Watterson wonders what is occupying Bowles now. He says he is going to Boston with Schurz and that Halstead is playing an unfriendly game with him., 1874 Apr 20
    - Henry Watterson tells Bowles that Ohio cannot be carried., 1875 Sep 15
    - Watterson tells Bowles he has been working since his return home. He speaks briefly of Blaine and compliments Bowles., 1877 May 17
    - Henry Watterson writes a friendly letter to Bowles asking how Bowles is and discussing a recent trip., 1877 May 24
    - I. Watson Webb sends Bowles a pamphlet which he wishes him to criticize honestly - irregardless of their friendship. He says that it is the duty of all editors to dispose ofcharlatans., 1875 Oct 15
    - I. Watson Webb advises Bowles that in looking over the pamphlet of Col. Canjun's that Mr. Kane was not dead but lost a leg., 1875 Dec
    - Thurlow Weed regrets that he cannot leave Albany before Tuesday, which will make it too late for him to confer with friends. He tells Bowles that his and Greeley's views coincide on the question of a certain Senator., 1853 Jan 22
    - David Ames Wells states that the notice of the position of the New York Supreme Court on stock certificates puts him in an altogether wary position., 1870 May 19
    - Wells discusses Garfield's responses on political issues. He mentions the United States Supreme Court's decision on taxation of railroads and state boards. He thinks the latter knocks the supremacy out of the New England tax system., 1874
    - D. A.Wells thinks that he has not a ghost of achancefor Congress., 1876 Mar 26
    - John Wells encloses a newspaper clipping in his letter to Bowles on judicial scandals and a condemnation of the sensational style of the paper., 1875 Jun 5
    - John Wells is dissatisfied with the tone of the Republican. He says that he and Bowles have different planes of thought; he hopes that they can discuss it in person sometime., 1875 Jun 28
    - Horace White praises the Republican and wants it sent to him in Rome. He says, after having been in Rome, that he believes the Papacy is a fraud; now he is in sympathy with Bismarck., 1875 Apr 13
    - Horace White tells Bowles that he has received a letter of his. He tells Bowles that Browne is justified in his course, since there is no other. He intimates that two suggestions have been made lately referring to Bryant's purchase of the Post. He thinks that the selection of Washburn would be the mere prolongation of Grant., 1876 Feb 18
    - John Greenleaf Whittier writes Charles Sumner a thank you for his help on the Cuban difficulty. Whittier speaks of the terrible butcheries occurring in France with the Commune. He says that the intelligent Republicans of Spain hate this., 1873 Nov 19
    - Whittier writes John H. Cook thanking him for a copy of an eloquent tribute to the memory of William F. Bartlett. Hehopesa statue will be set up on the banks of the Merrimac at the place of his birth., 1877 Nov 4
    - Charles Wesley Willard is thinking Bowles for his fight for freedom of the newspapers. He says that such decisions as Judge Endicott's will not breed libel suits., 1875 May 11
    - C. W. Willard tells Bowles that it is difficult to give the names of people who really want reform., 1875 Dec 3
    - Henry Wilson writes Bowles for a copy of a letter to which a Mr. Brown has referred., 1873 Oct 8
    - Henry Wilson thanks Bowles for a note and for not assailing him in the newspaper for actions at Philadelphia. He thanks Bowles for his help in Philadelphia and believes that the hour is at hand for a united party., 1855 Jun 23
    - Robert Charles Winthrop says that he has received a favor from Bowles and a copy of History of Western Massachusetts., no date